Finding Aid for Richard T. Liddicoat Papers, 1890-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard T. Liddicoat Papers 1890-1960
Liddicoat, Richard T. (Richard Thomas), b. 1891.
0.7 linear ft.
University of Michigan professor of engineering mechanics; papers include biographical information, writings, visual materials, and World War II letters of his two sons.
9948 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were transferred to the library though Eloise Liddicoat, daughter-in-law of Richard T. Liddicoat, in 1999. (Donor no. 8829 )
The collection is open for research.
In a formal statement conferring upon him the title of University of Michigan, Richard T. Liddicoat is remembered by colleagues with "affectionate esteem for his devotion to duty and for his friendliness and verve." This devotion led Professor Liddicoat to his most memorable research success, a helicopter, the ideas from which were later used in large jet powered models.
Professor Liddicoat was born in Ishpeming, Michigan of Cornish mining ancestry. In 1912 he enrolled in the University of Michigan College of Engineering, and was graduated with a baccalaureate in civil engineering in 1916. While he served in World War I, his young wife, Carmen, and their infant son, Richard ("Dick"), born in 1918, lived with his parents in Kearsarge, Michigan. Their son, William, ("Bill") was born several years later.
In 1919, Liddicoat joined the staff of the University of Michigan College of Engineering as an instructor in engineering mechanics. Research into helicopters would be one of his continuing interests at the university. In 1923, he created a device for illustrating critical speeds and resonance in helical springs and shafts. Throughout the next several years, Liddicoat also found time to continue his education doing graduate work at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, the California Institute of Technology and the University of Michigan. He obtained his master's degree in 1930 and his doctorate from the University of Michigan in 1940. Liddicoat was made assistant professor in 1925 and full professor in 1957. He retired from the university in 1962.
The collection of Richard Liddicoat is contained in four small series: Biographical Information/Personal Material, Writings, Visual Materials, and World War II Letters of his two sons Richard and William.
Subjects:
Liddicoat, Richard T. (Richard Thomas), b. 1891.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Engineering Mechanics.; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives, American.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Liddicoat, Richard T. (Richard Thomas), b. 1891.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Helicopters--American.; Teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Liddicoat, Richard T. (Richard Thomas), 1918-
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Biographical Information/Personal Material
  There is a small folder of Biographical Information/Personal Material, which includes brief biographical information contained in a letter written by the Board of Regents conferring upon Liddicoat the title of professor emeritus. Also found in this series is a narrative written by Eloise Liddicoat, the wife of his son Bill and a program from a school play of Liddicoat's son, Bill, which bears Jesse Owens autograph on the back.
  - Biographical citation, etc. (Box 1)
- Writings
  The Writings series includes Liddicoat's 1940 dissertation entitled "Analytical determination of coefficient of contraction for perfect or nonviscous liquid flowing through sharp-edged circular orifice in plane wall." There is also a report done in 1931 on his experimental study of human tolerance for horizontally applied accelerating forces and a manual that he wrote in 1946 on materials testing.
  - Dissertation, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Research Papers, 1931, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Laboratory Manual, 1946 (Box 1)
- Visual Material
  The Visual Material series includes both photographs and a motion picture film. The photographs depict the College of Engineering as it looked when housed in West Engineering, now known as West Hall. There are also photographs taken in Kearsarge and in Ann Arbor. Within a red album are photographs of the Liddicoat family in Kearsarge, many of these are of Professor Liddicoat's wife, Carmen, and their infant son, Richard, Jr., and some World War I memorabilia. Also included is a formal photograph of the Liddicoat family, and a portrait of Professor Liddicoat. There are a number of images documenting his education and career as an engineer at the University of Michigan. These include pictures of Liddicoat as a student surrounded by his undergraduate friends, as a teacher in a West Engineering classroom, with colleagues in his West Engineering office, photographs of the interior of his laboratory at the University of Michigan. The motion picture concerns Liddicoat's research with helicopters. The film has not yet been viewed because of broken sprockets and access will be prohibited until the film has been copied into a videotape format.
  - Photographs
    - Red Album, Liddicoat family in Kearsarge, Michigan, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Family Portrait, undated (Box 1)
    - West Engineering, undated (Box 1)
    - Helicopter Research, 1920-1927 (Box 1)
  - Motion picture of helicopter demonstration, ca. 1930, 16 mm; ca. 10 minutes (Map-case 11)
    (restricted access pending repair and duplication)
  - Engineering drawings of helicopter, June 1923, 2 items (Folder 1)
- World War II Letters
  The series World War II Letters includes letters written to Liddicoat and his wife from their two sons Richard and William serving in the military.
  - Letters written to parents by William and Richard Liddicoat during the war (Box 1)